### **Javier Torres**

Madrid Area, Spain

Vice President Business Operations, EMEA at Oracle Corporation

### Summary

Professional with significant international experience in the IT and Management Consulting Services Industries Strategic thinking, change management, leadership and communication skills Specialized on Business Operations, Sales & Marketing, IT & Operations Strategy and Corporate Strategy

### Experience

# Business Operations Vice President, Europe, Middle East and Africa at Oracle October 2015 - Present (7 months)

Overlooks all Sales Operations, Organization and Strategy issues for the different Sales Business Units (Technology, Applications and Systems) for EMEA (117 countries), reporting to the SVP for Operations & Strategy EMEA and APAC. Head of the Business Operations EMEA Management Team and member of the Oracle Extended EMEA Management team. Leads a team of Senior Operations Directors responsible for the Operations of the different Senior VPs of Products/ Regions, as well as central/divisional teams. 10 Direct reports and a total team of 200+ people. The Operations role is responsible to define, run and monitor processes and programs to support the Sales Organization in all business operations issues, including: Business Planning and Budgeting, Sales & Forecast Support, Knowledge Management & Internal communications, Sales Readiness, Sales tools (CRM, BI tools...) and process management; being specially key in the transformation of Oracle business and organization towards Cloud sales.

# Business Operations Senior Director, Europe, Middle East and Africa, Applications at Oracle June 2015 - September 2015 (4 months)

Overlooks all Sales Operations, Organization and Strategy issues for the Applications Business Unit for EMEA (117 countries), reporting to the VP for Operations EMEA and (dotted) to the SVP responsible for the Business Unit. Member of the Business Operations EMEA Management team and (by invitation) of the Oracle extended EMEA Management team. Leads a team of senior Operation Managers and Directors responsible for the Operations for the different Sales VPs of Products/regions, as well as a central team, for a total of 30 people, plus several resources in the Shared Service Centers of Romania and India. The EMEA Applications Business Unit has close to 3000 people and total sales above \$1Bn, including On Premise licenses and Cloud/ SaaS subscriptions. The Operations role is responsible to define, run and monitor processes and programs to support the Applications Sales Organization in all business operations issues, including: Business Planning and Budgeting, Sales & Forecast Support, Knowledge Management

& Internal communications, Sales Readiness and Sales tools (CRM, BI tools...) and process management; being specially key in the transformation of Oracle business and organization towards Cloud/SaaS sales.

# Business Operations Senior Director, Western Europe Applications at Oracle June 2014 - May 2015 (1 year)

Overlooked all Sales Operations, Organization and Strategy issues for the Applications Business Unit for Western Europe (14 countries), as well as the Sales Operations for SaaS (Cloud) for all EMEA. Led a team of 20 people. The Western Europe Applications Business Unit has close to 2000 people and total sales above \$700M\$, including On Premise licenses and Cloud/SaaS subscriptions. Supported the transformation to SaaS through a number of sales initiatives, including a new Go To Market and Sales Governance model, enabling 90%+ YoY growth rate and budget over-achievement on all the different solution/products.

# Business Operations and Demand Generation Director, Spain & Portugal at Oracle January 2012 - May 2014 (2 years 5 months)

1. Drive and Enable Technology License Sales organization in Iberia (>\$100M), overlooking all business management aspects: (a) Business Planning (go-to-market and budgeting) (b) Team governance to ensure strategy setting & execution, (c) Demand Generation, sales programs and productivity 2. Define, run and monitor processes and programs to support Technology License Organization in all business operations issues, including: Sales Support, Customer Care&Success, Knowledge Management & Internal communications, Sales Readiness and Sales tools (CRM, BI tools...) and process management 3. Overlook all business management aspects for Oracle Iberia (>\$500M), acting as Operations Director for the subsidiary, as part of the Country Management Team in Spain: (a) Business Planning, (b) M&A Integration, (c) Local governance processes across Bus (Country Management Team, Advisory Board...), (d) Leadership of local and EMEA strategic initiatives/projects 4. Lead Demand Generation for Oracle Iberia, including the coordination of the different Marketing events and campaigns as well as direct responsibility over the execution and budget management of the local Demand Generation efforts including, for example, VIP/C-Level events (e.g. Oracle Open World Spanish & Portuguese CIO Tour), direct marketing campaigns as well as sponsorships. 18 direct reports

#### Engagement Manager at McKinsey & Company September 2008 - January 2012 (3 years 5 months)

Analyzed critical strategic issues for some of the top companies in Spain, UK, Portugal, Africa and Latin America: led teams of 3-4 consultants and several clients, developed and presented recommendations to senior executives (CEO, CIO, COO and VP level); implemented cost savings and commercial optimization programs. Worked on IT/Technology, Operations, and Marketing issues mainly in the Telecommunications and Banking sectors. Example projects include: • Define the IT Security Strategy and organization for a major European Bank • Designed and implemented

the Operating Model for the Corporate/Investment Banking IT Organization of a of a major European Bank • Helped the Global CIO of a leading European telecom company to launch and implement Transformation initiatives, especially focusing on ADM outsourcing programs (>20 Mill. € annual savings) in Latin America, UK and Eastern Europe. • Developed the Global IT Strategy for leading European Telecom Company, including a new Operating model and the set up of a Global Shared Services Company to provide IT Global Services to the group • Designed and led the implementation of a major commercial transformation program (leading a central team of 9 senior and 20 junior "Commercial processes optimization" internal consultants) across all Business Units for an integrated Telco Operator • Led a initiative to capture synergies within the different Business Units of a leading European telecom company to optimize operationally its IT Workplace offer • Developing the Cloud Computing strategy for a leading European telecom company • Developed and deployed of a Lean Operations Transformation program in the Spanish subsidiary of a major retailer (>10 Mill.€ annual bottom line impact) • Conducted M&A due diligence and strategic advice, and prepare the Post Merger Integration plan for 3 Nigerian banks

#### Summer intern at Deutsche Bank

June 2007 - August 2007 (3 months)

Global Markets Summer Associate • Structured hybrid bond deals for corporate and financial corporations as part of the Debt Capital Markets group • Analyzed market drivers for hybrid bonds spreads during the beginning of the "credit crunch" and global financial crisis • Gave investment advice to the Spanish and Italian equity markets trading desk

#### Business Analyst at McKinsey

September 2004 - July 2006 (1 year 11 months)

Analyzed critical strategic issues for some of the top companies in Spain, Portugal and Latin America. Developed recommendations for C-level executives. Worked on Strategy and Marketing issues mainly in the Telecommunications and Banking sectors. Example of projects: • Developing the roadmap of the 3P offer of two leading European telecom companies, using market research • Defining the product value propositions for a leading Telco for entering and developing the ICT market for SMEs • Designed the branch expansion plan (locations, roll-out strategy and customer segment focus) for a mid-sized Retail Bank in Spain

#### Software Tester intern at Robert Bosch GmbH

June 2003 - August 2003 (3 months)

#### Software Developer Intern at Siemens

June 2002 - August 2002 (3 months)

### Education

Massachusetts Institute of Technology - Sloan School of Management

MBA, 2006 - 2008 Universidad Nacional de Educación a Distancia - U.N.E.D. Master, Mathematics, 2000 - 2006 Universidad Politécnica de Madrid Master of Engineering, Telecommunications, 1999 - 2004

## **Javier Torres**

Madrid Area, Spain

Vice President Business Operations, EMEA at Oracle Corporation



Profile Notes and Activity (1)

3/30/2016—Saved to "iwoca -- GM Spain" by Antonio Leone